Finding Aid for Frank D. Stella papers, ca. 1940-2010.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frank D. Stella papers circa 1940-2010
Stella, Frank D.
12 oversize volumes
49 linear feet (in 51 boxes)
2012094 Aa 2
Detroit businessman, active in many civic and philanthropic activities, a founder and president of the National Italian American Foundation and a founding director of Legatus, an organization of Catholic business leaders. The Frank D. Stella collection documents the career of a Detroit businessman, who devoted much of his time and energy to many philanthropic, cultural, and civic endeavors. The collection consists of his files from a selection of his organizational responsibilities relating to Italian American organizations and causes, to state and national Republican Party fund raising and campaigns, to Roman Catholic schools and organizations, and to the betterment of life (cultural, health services, etc.) of the greater Detroit area.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Mary Anne Stella (for the Stella family) and came to the library in April 2012. Additional materials were received in September 2012. Donor no. 10769.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Frank D. Stella was born January 21, 1919 in Jessup Pennsylvania. He graduated from the University of Detroit in 1941. Soon thereafter he was drafted into service with the U.S. Army Air Force. He was honorably discharged in 1946 as a Major. His company the F.D. Stella Products Company was established that same year as a designer and distributor of food services and dining equipment. Through his work, the firm would prosper, eventually designing, building, and financing restaurants for individuals and chains throughout the United States.
Stella was a man with a strong faith, a desire to serve his community, both in Detroit and beyond, and a pride in his Italian heritage. With these convictions Stella was involved (usually in a leadership position) in scores of organizations, projects, and initiatives. His detailed vita categorizes these activities into four area, public service, political, education and health care institutions, business organization, and civic, fraternal, religious, veterans and social organizations.
Of great importance to Stella was his work as vice chairman and president (since its founding) of the National Italian American Foundation. The National Italian American Foundation (NIAF) is a nonprofit, nonpartisan, educational foundation that promotes Italian American culture and heritage. NIAF serves as a resource on the Italian American community and has educational and youth programs including scholarships, grants, heritage travel and mentoring.
An active member of the Republican Party, Stella was skilled as a fund raiser in the Michigan Republic Party where he was finance chairman and a member of the party's executive committee and nationally where beginning in 1981 he was elected chairman of the National Republican Heritage Groups Council (NRHGC) of the Republican National Committee. That organization had been formed to encourage the participation of Republican ethnic groups in the political process. In both his work with NIAF and the NRHGC, Stella developed close ties with five Republican presidents. Stella was frequently mentioned as a leading candidate to be US Ambassador to Italy.
His Roman Catholic faith was important to Stella and it manifested itself in his many charitable endeavors and his business dealings. One example of this was his work with Legatus, an organization established in 1987 by Tom Monaghan. Frank Stella was a founding director and first president of the organization. Legatus was established as an association offering spiritual and business support for Catholic business leaders and their spouses.
Throughout his life, Stella was willing to take on an incredible number of responsibilities in organizations relating to education, health care, and community betterment. A fuller listing is in his vita (included with the papers). Among these was service as a member of the board of trustees of the University of Detroit; as chairman of Detroit Orchestra Hall where Stella spearheaded the effort to restore and renovate this important Detroit cultural institution; as member of the board of the Detroit Educational Television Foundation, licensee for WTVS Channel 56, Detroit Public Television; as member of the executive committee of the Detroit Casino Gaming Study Commission; and as member of the board of Mt. Carmel Mercy Hospital.
Frank D. Stella died September 27, 2010.
The Frank D. Stella collection documents the career of a Detroit businessman, who devoted much of his time and energy to many philanthropic, cultural, and civic endeavors. The collection consists of his files from a selection of his organizational responsibilities relating to Italian American organizations and causes, to state and national Republican Party fund raising and campaigns, to Roman Catholic schools and organizations, and to the betterment of life (cultural, health services, etc.) of the greater Detroit area.
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical / Personal; National Italian American Foundation; Republican Party activities; Orchestra Hall Renovation; Legatus; Various community, fraternal, and charitable activities; and Photographs. Portions of the collection are more fully processed than others. Most series are arranged, as Stella maintained the files, into broad chronological divisions. Only the Orchestra Hall series and the Photographs series have been arranged and described in more detail.
Subjects:
Stella, Frank D.; Detroit (Mich.). Casino Gaming Study Commission.; Detroit Educational Television Foundation.; Italian Americans.; Legatus (Organization); National Italian American Foundation.; Orchestra Hall (Detroit, Mich.); Republican National Heritage Groups Council.; Republican Party (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical / Personal
  - Biographical information; include family tribute given by Dan Stella at the Tree of Life Supper sponsored by the Jewish National Fund December 6, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Conversations with Frank D. Stella, 1 sound cassette (Box 1)
  - Collected materials; include records of Stella's art work collection, investments, property, etc. (Box 1)
  - World War II -- fragment of remembrances (Box 1)
  - Speeches and introductions to speeches (Box 1)
  - National Commercial Refrigerator Sales Association Addresses 1952, 1954 (Box 1)
    (each issue contains a speech given by Frank Stella)
  - Speech: Amigos De Ser Business Recognition ceremony 2000 (Box 1)
  - Articles written in Rediscovering Italy volume (Box 1)
  - Program and related from "An Evening with your Friend Frank D. Stella" June 28, 1999, include VHS cassette of the program (Box 1)
  - Travel diary 1960 (Box 1)
  - Album from United States Presidential Delegation to the 40th Anniversary of the Liberation of Rome June 1984 (Box 1)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation file compiled on Frank Stella (Box 1)
  - Michigan Dept. of Attorney General file compiled on Frank Stella (Box 1)
  - Yetzer family materials; also essay regarding Martha Yetzer Stella (Box 1)
  - Letters from politicians and other public figures 1970s-1980s, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (largely thank you letters, letters of congratulations, invitations, etc.)
  - Letters from William Milliken 1970s, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (largely responses to Stella recommendations of individuals for state offices)
  - Letters of US Presidents and Vice Presidents (Box 3)
  - Letters of Cabinet members, members of Congress, other political dignitaries (Box 3)
  - Letters and autographed programs of Luciano Pavarotti, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Autographs of various celebrities of event programs (Box 3)
  - Letters from various national and state public figures 1970-2008, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Letters and other materials of public figures - Presidents and Vice Presidents, Members of Congress, etc. 1980s-1990s (Box 51)
  - Invitations, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Christmas cards (Box 4)
  - Awards and citations given to Frank D. Stella (Box 5)
  - Awards and citations given to Frank D. Stella (Box 6)
    (continued)
  - Programs and other publications with mention of FS or relating to organizations in which he was active (Box 7)
  - Programs and other publications with mention of FS or relating to organizations in which he was active (Box 8)
  - Clippings about, or containing mention of, FS or his organizational activities (Box 9)
  - Clippings about, or containing mention of, FS or his organizational activities (Box 10)
  - Album of congratulatory letters upon FS receiving the Friends of Mercy Award from Mount Carmel Mercy Hospital March 2, 1984 (Volume 8)
  - Album of congratulatory letters received following his selection as recipient of the "Outstanding American Italian of the Year Award" by the 1976 Columbus Day Celebration Committee, October 10, 1976 (Volume 9)
  - Scrapbook 1970s, 1980s (Volume 10)
  - Military Service: World War II era letters, training materials, official directives, clippings, etc. (Box 11)
  - Military Service: World War II era letters, training materials, official directives, clippings, etc. (Box 12)
- National Italian American Foundation
  - Correspondence and other materials
    - September 1977-October 1980 (Box 13)
    - September 1980-March 1981 (Box 13)
    - October 1981-May 1982 (Box 13)
    - November 1981-August 1982 (Box 13)
    - September 1982-July 1983 (Box 13)
    - March 1985-May 1986 (Box 14)
    - November 1987-July 1988 (Box 14)
    - December 1987-March 1988 (Box 14)
    - October 1992-April 1994 (Box 15)
    - October 1992-December 1994 (Box 15)
    - April 1996-October 1996 (Box 15)
    - May 1996-December 1996 (Box 15)
    - August 1996-October 1996 (Box 15)
    - October 19, 1985 Tenth Anniversary Gala Dinner, program (Box 15)
    - April-June 1992 Mentor Program (Box 16)
    - October 1992-June 1993 (Box 16)
    - October 1992-September 1993 Scholarship Applications, Financial, Reports and Correspondence (Box 16)
    - September 1993-November 1993 (Box 16)
    - October 1993 Gala Dinner, Speech, Notes, Program (Box 16)
    - December 1993-October 1994 Correspondence, Reports, Financial (Box 16)
    - October 1994 Gala Dinner (Box 16)
    - October 1979-October 1980 Correspondence, Press Releases, Bios, Misc. (Box 17)
    - October 1984-December 1986 Correspondence (includes Nixon, Becker) (Box 17)
    - March 1986-December 1987 Correspondence, Reports, Clippings (Box 17)
    - November 1986-October 1987 Correspondence, Reports (Box 17)
    - July 1987 "Student Exchange Program Between Italy and the U.S." Final Report (Box 17)
    - 1992-1999 By-laws, Correspondence, Newsletter, Board of Directors (Box 18)
    - December 1997-January 1999 Nominating Committee, By-laws (Box 18)
    - April 1998-February 1999 Correspondence, Financial, Meeting Minutes (Box 18)
    - January 1980-March 1981 Correspondence, Clippings, Constitution, Minutes, Reports (Box 19)
    - April-June 1981 Correspondence, Minutes, Financial (Box 19)
    - April-June 1981 Correspondence, Newsletter, Financial, Report (Box 19)
    - June 1981-March 1982 Correspondence, Papers (Box 19)
    - December 1981-March 1982 Correspondence, Resumes, Reports, Financial (Box 19)
    - January-March 1982 Correspondence, Resumes, Reports, Financial (Box 19)
    - October 1989-2001 Board of Directors materials, Correspondence, Papers, Reports (Box 19)
    - October 1989-March 1992 Correspondence, Papers, Clippings (Box 20)
    - August 1990-November 1991 Correspondence (Box 20)
    - June-October 1991 Gala Dinner, Speech, Correspondence, Papers, Financial (Box 20)
    - August 1991-April 1992 Correspondence, Clippings, Printed (Box 20)
    - June-November 1992 Correspondence, Papers, Clippings, Agendas, Financial (Box 20)
    - July 1977-August 1982 Correspondence, Newsletters, Dinner Programs, News (Box 21)
    - August 1977-August 1982 Correspondence, Notes, Papers, Newsletters (Box 21)
    - April 1980-January 1981 Correspondence, Press Releases, Minutes, Newsletters, Papers, Vitas, Reports (Box 21)
    - July 1981-March 1983 Correspondence, Legal, Conference, Printed (Box 21)
    - June-December 1982 Correspondence, Clippings, Newsletter, Press Release (Box 21)
    - 1980-1992 Correspondence, Census, Addresses (Box 22)
    - 1987-2000 Correspondence, Biography, includes International Advisory (Box 22)
    - April 1987-October 2000 Minutes, Addresses, ComUnico Magazine (Box 22)
    - January 1994-July 1999 Correspondence, By-Laws, Lists, Articles, Programs, Financial (Box 22)
    - July 1995-April 1999 Correspondence, Papers, Clippings (Box 22)
    - December 1988-January 1990 Correspondence, Clippings, Minutes (Box 23)
    - March-November 1989 Correspondence (Box 23)
    - "Seminal Works in Italian Literature from the 1300s to the 1900s", undated (Box 24)
    - 1979-March 1981 Correspondence, Newspapers, Reports, all relating to Earthquake (Box 24)
    - May 1979-July 1987 Correspondence, Biography, Papers, Newsletters, Minutes, Financial (Box 24)
    - June 1986-February 1987 Correspondence, Addresses, Program, Newspapers (Box 24)
    - February 1987-July 1987 Correspondence, Programs (Box 24)
    - May 21, 1987 "A Literacy, Survival/Job Skills and Parenting Program for Italian and Vietnamese Women" (Box 24)
    - January 1989 "A Confidential Report of Feasibility Study" (Box 24)
    - October 1986-November 1990 Correspondence, Clippings, By-laws, Minutes, Financial, includes Board Committee (Box 25)
    - November 1987-October 1990 Columbus Commission (Box 25)
    - May 1988-December 1990 Correspondence, Reports, Clippings, includes Sports Hall of Fame (Box 25)
    - November 1990-June 1991 Correspondence, Minutes (Box 25)
    - 1976-1985 undated, Speeches (Box 26)
    - October 1981-July 1983 Correspondence (Box 26)
    - January 1990-July 1992 Correspondence (Box 26)
    - October 1990 Gala Dinner (Box 26)
    - Summer 1977-April 1979 Washington Newsletters (Box 27)
    - August 1981-January 1984 Correspondence, Constitution, Reports, Programs, Minutes (Box 27)
    - May-July 1982 Correspondence, Printed, Annual Report (Box 27)
    - July 1982-November 1983 A.P. Giannini, Correspondence, Press Releases, Dinner, Budget (Box 27)
    - September 1982-November 1983 Correspondence (Box 27)
    - February-November 1983 Correspondence, Speeches, Reports, Press Releases (Box 27)
    - 1978-1991 undated, Award/Dinner Programs (Box 28)
    - 1980-1992 Newsletters, Washington (Box 28)
    - October 1986 Newspapers, Printed (Box 28)
    - 1987, 1999 Newspaper, Clippings (Box 28)
    - 1989-2000 Newsletters, Other (Box 28)
    - April 1989-March 1990 Correspondence, Board of Directors, Clippings, Constitution (Box 28)
    - March 1994-August 1998 Correspondence, Tribute, Printed (Box 28)
    - January 1994-June 1998 Correspondence, Board of Directors, Reports, Newspaper, Addresses (Box 29)
    - May 1996-July 1997 Correspondence, Reports, Board of Directors (Box 29)
    - July 1996-January 1998 Correspondence, Reports, Board of Directors, Clippings, Newsletter (Box 29)
    - October 1996-March 1998 Correspondence, Clippings, Board of Directors, Reports, Program (Box 29)
    - April-November 1997 Correspondence, includes Confartigianato (Box 29)
    - August-October 1997 Correspondence, Speeches, Board of Directors, Reports (Box 29)
    - July-November 1998 Correspondence, Board of Directors, Reports (Box 29)
    - 1993-2000 Gala Dinner Books (Box 30)
- Republican Party
  - Republican National Conventions
    - 1980 Detroit, MI (Box 31)
    - 1984 Dallas, TX (Box 31)
    - 1988 New Orleans (Box 31)
    - 1992 Houston, TX (Box 31)
      (Stella was alternate delegate)
    - 1996 San Diego, CA (Box 32)
    - 2000 Philadelphia, PA (Box 32)
  - National Campaign Files
    - 1992 Presidential Campaign
      - Catholics for Bush (Box 32)
      - Independent Business Coalition (Box 32)
      - Italian Americans for Bush (Box 32)
      - National Coalitions (Box 32)
    - 2004 Presidential Campaign (Box 32)
  - Post National Campaign materials
    - Inaugurations
      - 1985 (Box 32)
      - 2001 (Box 32)
    - 1988-1989 post-election correspondence; letters relating to the possible selection of Frank Stella as US Ambassador to Italy (Box 32)
    - 1989 letters relating to the possible selection of Frank Stella as US Ambassador to the Vatican (Box 32)
    - 2000-2001 letters relating to the possible selection of Frank Stella as US Ambassador to the Vatican (Box 32)
    - 2004-2005 letters relating to the possible selection of Frank Stella as US Ambassador to the Vatican (Box 32)
  - State Campaign Materials
    - 1976 (Box 33)
    - 1978 (Box 33)
    - 1983 State Finance Committee records (Box 33)
      (Frank Stella was Finance Chairman of the Michigan Republican Party)
    - 1983-1985, 5 folders (Box 33)
    - 1993 Governor's Gala (Box 33)
    - 1994 Spencer Abraham for US Senate, 2 folders (Box 33)
    - 1994 John A. Schall for Congress (13th District), 2 folders (Box 33)
    - 1994 John Smietanka for State Attorney General (Box 33)
  - Republican National Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council
    (Frank Stella was chairman)
    - Informational records 1984-1992 (Box 34)
    - Informational material: rosters, constitution, brochure 1992 (Box 34)
    - 1984-1986 (Box 34)
    - 1986-1991 (Box 35)
    - 1992-1994 (Box 36)
    - 1998-circa 2000 (Box 36)
  - Mixed activities
    - State Finance Committee and Republican National Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council 1970s-1980s (Box 50)
- Orchestra Hall Renovation
  The Orchestra Hall Renovation series is primarily comprised of files related to Stella's involvement with the effort to restore Detroit's Orchestra Hall. It also includes files related to his involvement with the Detroit Symphony Orchestra, Michigan Opera Theater, and the renovation of the Detroit Opera House. The material in this series includes correspondence, minutes and agendas for various committee meetings, membership lists, construction documents, and publications. The material in this series related to the funding of the Orchestra Hall restoration is especially strong. Also of interest are early documents detailing the restoration plans and their anticipated costs, which are concentrated in the Chronological Files, between the years of 1984 and 1987.
  - Administrative Files
    - Administrative Binder 1987 (Box 37)
    - Ambassador's Project 1987 (Box 37)
    - Annual Meeting of the Members (Box 37)
    - Background (Box 37)
    - Board Membership (Box 37)
    - Budget 1994 (Box 37)
    - Bylaws undated (Box 37)
    - Campaign Feasibility Study 1991 (Box 37)
    - Clippings (Box 37)
    - Concerto for Community and Orchestra Campaign 2000 (Box 37)
    - Dedication 1983 (Box 37)
    - Endowment Campaign 1993 (Box 37)
    - Financial Statements 1985, 1990 (Box 37)
    - Merger (Box 37)
    - Neighborhood Opportunity Fund 1983 (Box 37)
    - Orchestra Hall Completion Report 1986 (Box 37)
    - Orchestra Hall Master Plan 1987 (Box 37)
    - Orchestra Hall Parking Study 1984 (Box 37)
    - Organizational Charts (Box 37)
    - Outline Report 1987 (Box 37)
    - Press Releases (Box 37)
    - Program Analysis 1987 (Box 37)
    - Programming (Box 37)
    - Restoration (Box 37)
    - Restoration and Rehabilitation Report 1987 (Box 37)
    - Schematic Phase 1985 (Box 37)
    - Selden Ave 1985-1988 (Box 37)
    - Self Appraisal Questionnaire Summary 1984 (Box 37)
    - Strategic Plan 1986 (Box 37)
    - Update Report 1987 (Box 37)
  - Chronological Files 1982-1987, 7 folders (Box 37)
  - Chronological Files 1987-1995, 8 folders (Box 38)
  - Committees
    - Advisory Committee (Box 38)
    - Ball in the Hall Committee (Box 38)
    - Board of Directors
      - Handbook 1986 (Box 38)
      - Meetings, 3 folders (Box 38)
    - Campaign for Orchestra Hall Organizing Committee (Box 38)
    - Capital Campaign (Box 38)
    - Concert Master's Club
      - General (Box 38)
      - Meetings (Box 38)
      - Reports (Box 38)
      - Solicitation Kits (Box 38)
      - Solicitation Materials (Box 38)
    - Development Committee (Box 38)
    - Executive Committee, 2 folders (Box 38)
    - Finance Committee (Box 38)
    - Fund Development Committee (Box 38)
    - Membership Committee (Box 38)
    - Negotiating Committee (Box 38)
    - Nominating Committee (Box 38)
    - Operating Board (Box 39)
    - Planning Committee (Box 39)
    - Public Affairs Committee (Box 39)
    - Restoration Committee (Box 39)
    - Volunteer Council (Box 39)
  - Detroit Symphony Orchestra
    - Board Member Manual (Box 39)
    - DSO Contract (Box 39)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 39)
  - Michigan Opera Theater
    - Board of Directors (Box 39)
    - Building Committee (Box 39)
    - Detroit Opera House (Box 39)
    - Inaugural Gala 1996 (Box 39)
    - Press Conference 1995 (Box 39)
    - Public Affairs Task Force (Box 39)
- Legatus
  (correspondence, memoranda, board materials)
  - 1987 (Box 40)
  - 1988
    - Miscellaneous records (Box 40)
    - Legatus Michigan Directory 1988 (Box 40)
    - Rome trip October-November 1988 (Box 40)
  - 1989
    - Miscellaneous records (Box 40)
    - Legatus Vision-memo written by Michael Schwartz February 5, 1989 (Box 40)
    - National Catholic Reporter article by Russ Bellant with response by Frank Stella and others (Box 40)
  - 1990
    - Miscellaneous records (Box 40)
    - National Conference of Legatus, Philadelphia May 1990 (Box 40)
    - European Trip September 1990 (Box 40)
  - 1991
    - Miscellaneous records (Box 40)
    - Membership Survey, Michigan Results (Box 40)
    - Legatus Michigan Chapter Roster circa 1991 (Box 40)
  - 1992, 2 folders (Box 40)
  - 1993
    - Miscellaneous records (Box 41)
    - Board of Directors meeting February 20-21, 1993 (Box 41)
  - 1994 (Box 41)
  - 1995 (Box 41)
  - 1996
    - Miscellaneous records, 2 folders (Box 41)
    - Board of Directors and Strategic Planning meetings June 28-29, 1996 (Box 41)
    - Board of Directors meeting October 18, 1996 (Box 41)
    - Membership Survey Report (Box 41)
  - 1997
    - Miscellaneous records, 3 folders (Box 41)
    - Board of Directors meeting February 6, 1997 (Box 41)
    - Board of Directors meeting June 6, 1997 (Box 41)
    - 1997 Business Plan (Box 41)
  - 1998
    - Miscellaneous records (Box 41)
    - Board of Directors meeting February 4, 1998 (Box 41)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Committee meetings June 18-19, 1998 (Box 41)
    - First Friday Report December 1998 (Box 41)
  - 1999
    - Miscellaneous records (Box 41)
    - First Friday Report January 1999 (Box 41)
    - Board of Directors meeting February 3-4, 1999 (Box 41)
  - 2002
    - Board of Directors and Executive Committee meetings February 7-8, 2002 (Box 42)
  - Other files
    - By-laws-International and Chapter (Box 42)
    - Development Manual (Box 42)
    - More Than Lip Service (seminar on business ethics) (Box 42)
    - Long-Range Strategic Plan (Box 42)
    - Publications (Box 42)
    - Various (Box 42)
    - Legatus newsletter (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 42)
- Various community, fraternal, and charitable activities
  - Italian Heritage Organizations
    - Christopher Columbus Quincentenary Jubilee Commission 1991-1993, 3 folders (Box 43)
      (include records of Michigan Commission also)
    - Christopher Columbus Statue Beautification Committee, Detroit 1985-1993 (Box 43)
    - Dante Alighieri Society 1979-1991 (Box 43)
    - Italian American Cultural Society 1984-1991 (Box 43)
    - Statue of Enrico Caruso Society, Dearborn Heights, MI 1988 (Box 43)
    - Universitas Internationalis Coluccio Salutati (UICS)-American Foundation 1986-1987 (Box 43)
      (Frank Stella was Executive President)